John P. Lanigan Papers
John P. Lanigan Papers
1965-1971
Lanigan, John P.
5.25 linear ft
193 original editorial cartoons and printed material
149121
Biographical History
John P. “Jack” Lanigan (1922-2000) was an American editorial cartoonist for the New Bedford, Massachusetts Standard Times.
John P. Lanigan was born in Chicago on October 8, 1922 and served in the South Pacific during World War II and participated in the Guadalcanal campaign. He studied at the Art Institute of Chicago and the Art Students' League but was recalled into military service during the Korean War and worked with the atomic bomb testing unit. Upon his discharge, he pursued freelance work and became the editorial cartoonist for the Standard Times in 1964.
Lanigan held membership in the American Association of Editorial Cartoonists and his cartoons were selected for the Best Editorial Cartoons of the Year series. His cartoons were exhibited as part of the 1970 International Cartoon Exhibition in Athens, Greece, and were included in the Man and His World International Fine Arts Exhibition at Expo 67 in Montreal.
John P. Lanigan retired in 1987 to the Lake Luzerne, New York area and died of cancer on March 25, 2000.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John P. Lanigan Papers are organized into 2 series. The first series, Cartoons contains 193 original editorial cartoons. The majority of the cartoons have been approximately dated based on when they were donated. The cartoons were produced with ink, pencil and dot screening on a variety of weights of illustration board. Dimensions vary and notations are included in pencil. Of interest is a cartoon in Box 4 Folder 2 that Lanigan burned the edges of to create a charred effect.
Lanigan often filled the entire frame with imagery and juxtaposed various elements in a collage like fashion. Many cartoons actually contained several cartoons about completely different subjects. In his portrayals of political figures, Lanigan often drew very realistic looking heads on very cartoon-looking bodies while other figures were portrayed as inanimate objects such as knives (Robert F. Kennedy) and spots on x-rays (Lyndon B. Johnson).
The Printed Material series contains 1 folder of clippings of Lanigan's published cartoons.
Arrangement of the Collection
The Cartoons are arranged in chronological order where there is a specific date with undated cartoons appearing in folders for their approximate year.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Lanigan, John P.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Spock, Benjamin, 1903-1998 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; New Bedford standard-times.; United States. Congress -- Caricatures and cartoons.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Massachusetts.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- Massachusetts.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Political cartoons.; Pollution -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Taxation -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John P. Lanigan, 1966-1971.
Inventory
- Cartoons, Click here for a list of specific dates. See below for an index to the cartoons.
  - 1966 Jan, Mar - Apr, Jun, 7 items (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - 1966 Jul, Oct - Dec, 7 items (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - circa 1966, 4 items (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - 1967 Jan, 4 items (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
  - 1967 Mar - Aug, 9 items (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - 1967 Sep - Dec, 10 items (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
  - circa 1967, 9 items (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
  - 1968 Jan - Mar, 8 items (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
  - 1968 Apr - Jun, 12 items (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
  - 1968 Jul - Aug, series of cartoons, "The Players" in which the 1968 presidential candidates are portrayed as characters in famous plays; 4 items (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
  - circa 1968, 7 items (Oversize 3, Folder 1)
  - circa 1968, 8 items (Oversize 3, Folder 2)
  - 1969 Apr, 1 items (Oversize 3, Folder 3)
  - circa 1969, 7 items (Oversize 3, Folder 4)
  - circa 1969, 6 items (Oversize 3, Folder 5)
  - circa 1970, 11 items (Oversize 4, Folder 1)
  - circa 1970, 11 items (Oversize 4, Folder 2)
  - circa 1970, 11 items (Oversize 4, Folder 3)
  - circa 1970, 9 items (Oversize 5, Folder 1)
  - circa 1970, 10 items (Oversize 5, Folder 2)
  - circa 1970, 5 items (Oversize 5, Folder 3)
  - circa 1971, 10 items (Oversize 6, Folder 1)
  - circa 1971, 10 items (Oversize 6, Folder 2)
  - circa 1971, 13 items (Oversize 6, Folder 3)
- Printed Material
  - Clippings and printed cartoons, 1965; 1967-1968;; undated; The clippings are photocopies of the originals as they appeared on scrapbook pages. (Box 1)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Agnew, Spiro T. B6F1-B6F3
airline industry B6F1
American bison B6F1
anti-trust laws B6F3
automobile accidents B1F5 B1F7 B6F2
Brennan Jr., William J. B1F4
Britain B1F5-B1F6
budget B1F2 B2F1
Canada B6F3
cancer B4F2
Carswell, George Harrold B5F2
Castro, Fidel B1F5
charity B1F2 B1F6-B1F7
Warren, Earl B1F6
China B1F1-B1F2
civil rights B1F7
Clark, Tom B1F4
Cloherty, Peter J. B1F5
college students B1F2 B3F4
communism B1F5-B1F6
Congress B1F4 B2F1 B3F1 B3F4-B4F2 B5F3
consumers B1F1
crime B1F6 B2F1-B2F2 B3F4 B4F1 B6F3
Czechoslovakia B2F1 B2F3 B3F2
de Gaulle, Charles B1F1 B1F3 B2F2 B3F1 B3F4
Democratic National Convention B2F2
Democratic Party B2F2 B3F1 B6F2
demonstrations B1F3 B1F7
draft B1F2
driving B1F2 B1F6 B2F2 B5F2
drug use B1F1 B4F3 B6F3
Earth Day B4F3
economy B4F2 B5F3 B6F2
education B1F1 B3F1 B3F3
elections B1F3 B1F5 B2F2
espionage B6F1
evolution B5F2
farming B4F1
food B4F1
food prices B4F1
Ford, Gerald R. B5F1
France B1F1 B2F2-B2F3 B3F4 B6F3
freedom B1F2 B4F2
Germany B1F6
gold reserve B2F1
Goldberg, Arthur B1F1
Great Society B1F3
gun control B2F2
Harriman, W. Averell B2F3
Hatfield, Mark B4F1
healthcare B1F6-B1F7
highway construction B4F2
hijacking B6F2
Ho Chi Minh B1F7
holidays B1F2 B1F4 B1F6 B3F2
housing B2F2
Humphrey, Hubert B1F6 B2F2-B3F1
Hungary B3F2
industry (general) B5F2
insurance B1F2 B1F5-B1F6 B4F3
investors B5F2
Iraq B3F5
isolation B1F1
Israel B2F3
Japan B5F1
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F4-B1F6 B2F1-B2F2 B3F1 B3F4
judicial system B5F1
Douglas, William O. B5F1
White, Byron B1F6
Keller, Helen B2F2
Kennedy, Robert F. B2F1-B2F2
Kennedy, Ted B6F2
labor B5F2 B6F2
Lebanon B6F3
Lincoln, Abraham B1F6 B2F1
Lindsay, John B6F2
Maddox, Lester B3F1 B6F3
Massachusetts B1F1-B1F2 B1F5 B1F7 B2F2 B3F4-B4F3 B5F1 B5F3-B6F1 B6F3
McCarthy, Eugene B1F7-B3F1
McGovern, George B3F1 B4F1
McNamara, Robert B1F6
Meany, George B6F2
Medicaid B1F6
Medicare B1F4
Middle East B1F5 B4F2
military B1F2
Miller, Arthur B1F3
Morse, Wayne B1F5
Nader, Ralph B6F1
Nasser, Gamal Abdel B1F5-B1F6 B2F3
New York B1F4 B6F2
New York City B1F1
Nixon, Richard M. B2F1 B2F3-B3F1 B3F4 B4F2-B4F3 B5F2-B6F1
oceanography B1F7
oil B4F2-B4F3 B6F3
Olympics B2F1
Palestine B6F3
peace B1F1 B1F7 B2F3
Pentagon B6F1
Poland B3F2
police B1F4 B6F3
pollution B4F1 B4F3 B5F1-B5F2
Pompidou, Georges B5F2
Pope Paul VI B1F1
Poseidon Affair B4F1
poverty B1F1 B1F5
Ramsey, Paul B1F1
Republican Party B1F1 B2F1 B5F1
riots B1F7
Rockefeller, Nelson B2F3 B3F2
Romania B3F2
Romney, George W. B1F5
Russell, Bertrand B2F2
Russia B3F2
schools B1F4 B5F1 B6F1
science B1F1
shipbuilding B6F2
Smith, Margaret Chase B5F2
smoking B2F3 B4F2
Soviet Union B1F1 B1F5 B2F3
space exploration B4F3 B5F1
Spock, Benjamin B1F6 B2F2 B5F1
sports B1F5-B2F1
strikes B1F1 B5F2
Supreme Court B1F4 B5F1
taxes B1F1 B1F3 B1F5 B3F1 B3F5 B6F1-B6F2
television B4F2
terrorism B6F3
textile industry B5F1
Thant, U. B4F2
Townsend Plan B2F2
treason B1F4
tyranny B1F2
U.S. flag B1F1 B1F3 B1F5
U.S. Treasury B1F4
UNICEF B1F7
United Arab Republic B1F7 B4F2
United Auto Workers B6F3
United Nations B1F1-B1F2 B3F2 B4F1-B4F2
universities B1F7 B3F4 B5F1-B5F2 B6F1
USS Liberty B1F5
USS Pueblo B2F2
Vietnam War B1F1-B1F5 B2F2-B2F3 B4F1 B5F2 B6F1
violence B2F1
Volpe, John B1F1
voting B3F5 B5F1 B6F3
Wallace, George B3F1-B3F2 B5F3
war B3F2
weather B1F1 B1F5-B1F6 B2F1
welfare B6F3
women's rights B4F1
Young Jr., Whitney M. B6F1
Zedong, Mao B1F1